guys a bunch of people mentioned me in
this one so let's do this x squared plus
y squared equals 25 and the 2x plus y
equals 10 and we want to evaluate X Plus
y so first let's focus on the 2x plus y
equals 10. let's get the Y all by itself
let's subtract 2x from both sides on the
left hand side we just have y and on the
right hand side we have 10 minus 2X and
this is important so let's put a box
around it next let's focus on the x
squared plus y squared equals 25. let's
bring it down and in the place of this y
right here I want to plug in 10 minus 2x
so now this is 10 minus 2x being squared
so we're going to multiply 10 minus 2x
times 10 minus 2x 10 times 10 is 100 10
times negative 2x is negative 20x
negative 2x times 10 is negative 20x and
negative 2x times negative 2x is
positive 4x squared and these two can
combine to become negative 40x let's
bring down the x squared and bring down
the equals 25. anytime I do one of these
several people always mention why don't
I do this shortcut well I did try it out
and it ended up not being much of a
shortcut so it low as nicely as this
method in these videos so now let's
combine like terms x squared plus 4x
squared is 5X squared we can bring down
the negative 40x and if we subtract 25
from both sides 100 minus 25 is 75 and
25 minus 25 is zero from here all three
of these terms are divisible by 5 so
let's divide both sides by 5. each of
these terms will divide by 5 to give us
x squared minus eight X plus 15 and it's
still equal to zero and now to solve
this we want to factor we want two
numbers that will add to negative 8 and
multiply to positive 15. well negative 3
plus negative 5 will give us negative 8
and negative 3 times negative 5 will
give us positive 15. so these are the
factors of this so from here if this
equals 0 or if this equals 0 the whole
thing will equal zero because anything
times 0 equals zero so we have this or
this and if we add 3 to both sides we
get x equals 3 and if we add 5 to both
sides we get x equals five so X can be
either 3 or 5. so we don't really need
any of this work anymore and let's bring
these up here since our goal to figure
out what is X Plus y we want to find out
our corresponding y values so let's use
this 2x plus y equals 10. we'll copy it
down solve for y in the place of this x
let's plug in 3. 2 times 3 is 6. let's
subtract 6 from both sides and we get y
equals 4. and same thing for this one if
we plug in 5 for the X 2 times 5 is 10
subtract 10 from both sides and we get y
equals zero these are our two possible
scenarios and we want to evaluate X Plus
y for each of these scenarios for the
first scenario X Plus y ends up being 3
plus 4 which is equal to 7 and for this
scenario X Plus Y is 5 plus 0 which is
equal to five and these are the two
possible answers to the question X Plus
y equals seven or X Plus y equals five
and if you want to see what this looks
like graphically here it is right here
the x squared plus y squared equals 25
is the red circle and the 2x plus y
equals 10 is this blue line and here's
our two intersection points three four
and five zero how exciting